<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>GeoLift Blog</title>
        <link>https://facebookincubator.github.io/GeoLift/blog</link>
        <description>GeoLift Blog</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 Jun 2022 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Meta Blueprint Course - Measure the Incremental Impact of Your Marketing With GeoLift]]></title>
            <link>https://facebookincubator.github.io/GeoLift/blog/blueprint-geolift</link>
            <guid>blueprint-geolift</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jun 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Blueprint]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://facebook-cdn.exceedlms.com/uploads/resource_hero_pictures/targets/603247/w2400/2400-x-650.png?Policy=eyJTdGF0ZW1lbnQiOlt7IlJlc291cmNlIjoiaHR0cHM6Ly9mYWNlYm9vay1jZG4uZXhjZWVkbG1zLmNvbS91cGxvYWRzL3Jlc291cmNlX2hlcm9fcGljdHVyZXMvdGFyZ2V0cy82MDMyNDcvdzI0MDAvMjQwMC14LTY1MC5wbmciLCJDb25kaXRpb24iOnsiRGF0ZUxlc3NUaGFuIjp7IkFXUzpFcG9jaFRpbWUiOjE2NTQ1NDY3OTh9fX1dfQ__&amp;Signature=DXer4smR166~jI0jTqOkQUTKAd2tK2LhYVNa0H0qJ7iPsaJNAQNHxOLEwdbt~4lY0rUA5xhPQyYJWsgT9uwgUKvu33inf0SKAGvDCN2bfdfOWuwx1Na0ByjojRPWgBKZD3V43IvpGqq-zdtU4h9BJ4qh5btYF172hMcNciOQbPDLRurT55Nx0IdJpvRq09dZqOzK22-Eoa3B0kOqL5y4UzIbgw0MjIjj2sSpu2tCTpCoHjxQ6gzZQ~1ecdfFY7B1kC52kPmBFYrREjN6DQvELBKmxYfbukVSaD5YO34dUYOTzuxIecgHPpjy97VOueh6Zu1MjpEbLi0SWHCvYnBigg__&amp;Key-Pair-Id=APKAJINUZDMKZJI5I6DA" alt="Blueprint"/></p><h2>New GeoLift Course by Meta Blueprint</h2><p>We are excited to share the launch of our new self-paced step-by-step tutorial to teach you how to run geo-experiments with GeoLift!</p><p>Geo experimentation can help advertisers establish causal relationships between their marketing efforts and a business outcome. While there are many tools to run impact analysis, setting up these types of experiments can be a challenge. That is why we have developed GeoLift, one of the newest additions to the Meta Open Source library.</p><p>As an open source tool, we want to continue democratization of geo experimentation knowledge. Today, we are announcing that we have just published our first virtual and free <a href="https://www.facebookblueprint.com/student/path/253063-geolift-marketing-measurement?sid=cd9a46bc-9685-4af4-8ac3-4482e858fba9&amp;sid_i=5">course on GeoLift on Meta Blueprint</a>.</p><p>In just 50 minutes, we will go over:</p><ul><li>Introduction to GeoLift - The features of the GeoLift solution and how it can support your business goals, comparing it to other existing geo experimentation methods.</li><li>Design a GeoLift Experiment - The steps and data required to design a GeoLift experiment.</li><li>Apply Best Practices With GeoLift - How to apply best practices with GeoLift experiments and evaluate whether you can use other experiments instead.</li></ul><p>Optional Lessons for the more technical audience:</p><ul><li>Implement the GeoLift Solution - How to run simulations and determine the best test market for a GeoLift experiment.</li><li>Run a Successful GeoLift Experiment - How to use the GeoLift solution R code to run a successful GeoLift experiment</li></ul><p>Happy testing!</p><p><a href="https://www.facebookblueprint.com/student/path/253063-geolift-marketing-measurement?sid=cd9a46bc-9685-4af4-8ac3-4482e858fba9&amp;sid_i=5/"><img src="https://facebook-cdn.exceedlms.com/uploads/organizations/branding_logos/977/full/Meta_Blueprint_lockup_positive_primary_RGB__281_29.png?1636402332&amp;Policy=eyJTdGF0ZW1lbnQiOlt7IlJlc291cmNlIjoiaHR0cHM6Ly9mYWNlYm9vay1jZG4uZXhjZWVkbG1zLmNvbS91cGxvYWRzL29yZ2FuaXphdGlvbnMvYnJhbmRpbmdfbG9nb3MvOTc3L2Z1bGwvTWV0YV9CbHVlcHJpbnRfbG9ja3VwX3Bvc2l0aXZlX3ByaW1hcnlfUkdCX18yODFfMjkucG5nPzE2MzY0MDIzMzIiLCJDb25kaXRpb24iOnsiRGF0ZUxlc3NUaGFuIjp7IkFXUzpFcG9jaFRpbWUiOjE2NTQ1NDczOTR9fX1dfQ__&amp;Signature=NDbZh2nCfpeJ3MBdHv2-AATzLGuX7YFD4YCcRCwDLbM~mEHBkT0a30yUFa86GnQVJhsLBqW2~jNE4SDTTf9gFkfJ0wg2HfT8dX1SAJoVkD~H7oNPy21QDVXXiDNoMrxoouuSz64OYIjSlUEtVEkkBYF1B60~ErquO7C4ubmGv49hbCOBuLl-6B0ZFQYnYocScAlG0QNuezMG6AhxSxPKOV-zQO5YPUvqMd~hCKmOkeqTsPONJ4Fv8obG-8SET7NGU3Hqen3pG2CRiQqAlZ1EKb0~FA59Z47RMIgsS-FM~EtkxbhRLSwvp9Ccfnc2YYDN3Sae~sIy~-aFyVsJnXV1oA__&amp;Key-Pair-Id=APKAJINUZDMKZJI5I6DA" alt="MetaBlueprint"/></a></p>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Inverse GeoLift - inference done cheaper]]></title>
            <link>https://facebookincubator.github.io/GeoLift/blog/inverse-geolift</link>
            <guid>inverse-geolift</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 12 May 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[TL;DR:]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>TL;DR:</h2><ul><li>Inverse GeoLifts help advertisers reduce geo experiment holdout sizes by inverting who sees ads: they show ads to the control group and do not show ads to the treatment group.</li><li>Given that geo-experiments require large control groups, Inverse GeoLifts are a good way of reducing holdout groups and opportunity cost without losing testing accuracy.</li><li>While Standard GeoLifts are great tools to measure a new media activity, ongoing media is best tested with an Inverse GeoLift.</li><li>MMM calibration: Standard GeoLifts are straightforward inputs into MMMs, while Inverse GeoLifts have a larger complexity for this use case.</li></ul><h2>Introduction and motivation</h2><p>GeoLift is an end-to-end solution that empowers you to determine the real effect of media via geographical experiments.</p><ul><li><strong>It’s causal.</strong>  GeoLift follows the KPI of a treatment group and compares it to what would have happened to that treatment group, if they had not been treated.  This is what we call a counterfactual.  The latter is built off of control locations that will not be exposed to the treatment effect and paired as close as possible to the treatment group, prior to the test.</li><li><strong>It’s transparent.</strong>  Being an open source package <a href="https://github.com/facebookincubator/GeoLift">hosted on Github</a>, the code is freely available for everyone to use and inspect.</li><li><strong>It sets you up for success.</strong>  There are many packages that help you analyze geographical quasi-experiments.  There’s only one that runs power analysis via simulations to help the user define where the treatment should be applied, on top of the standard analysis module.</li><li>It’s based on <a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/01621459.2021.1929245">cutting-edge econometric models</a>.</li></ul><p>In order to construct a robust counterfactual, GeoLift usually requires more than half the amount of available locations to be part of the control group.  This is because the counterfactual is created as a linear combination of the units in the pool of controls, therefore, richer pools tend to provide more robust counterfactuals.  Standard GeoLifts can be a great setup when you are trying to measure the positive effect that new media has on your business.</p><p>However, <strong>it can be detrimental to run an experiment with a large holdout when you would like to measure ongoing media efforts</strong>.  This has to do with the opportunity cost of running a test.  When you are holding out media from certain locations, your total KPI will decrease by the effect that media has in those locations, scaled by the size of the holdout.</p><p><img src="https://github.com/facebookincubator/GeoLift/blob/main/website/static/img/OppCost.png?raw=true" alt="OppCost"/></p><h2>A new hope</h2><p>A great way to reduce holdout size without compromising experiment accuracy is to <strong>flip GeoLift on its head</strong>: instead of showing media to the treatment group and holding out the control group, you holdout the treatment group and show media to the control group.  This is what we refer to as an Inverse GeoLift.</p><p><img src="https://github.com/facebookincubator/GeoLift/blob/main/website/static/img/InverseLiftTable.png?raw=true" alt="InverseTable"/></p><p>Inverse GeoLifts have a different interpretation than Standard GeoLifts.  Instead of measuring the contribution that media is having on the treatment locations, you are measuring the opportunity cost that holding out media has on the treatment locations.</p><p>The main assumption here is that positive and negative effects are interchangeable.  In other words, if you would run a Standard or an Inverse GeoLift, the only thing that would change is the sign of the effect, not its absolute value.  <strong>Don’t worry</strong>: when setting up a GeoLift and deciding which is the best treatment group for the experiment, the difference between the detected effect and the true effect is a variable that we are taking into account to rank different location combinations. Treatment setups that have a low difference are preferred and will be highly ranked.  <a href="https://github.com/facebookincubator/GeoLift/blob/main/vignettes/GeoLift_Walkthrough.md#power-analysis">Check here</a> to see what the ranking variables look like in our Walkthrough.</p><p><img src="https://github.com/facebookincubator/GeoLift/blob/main/website/static/img/TypesGeoLift.png?raw=true" alt="TypesGeoLift"/></p><h2>Tips for building and analyzing an Inverse GeoLift</h2><h3>Determine budget for the test.</h3><p>As long as you know your Cost Per Incremental Conversion (CPIC), Standard GeoLifts will tell you the minimum budget that you should invest in the treatment group.  For Inverse GeoLifts, we have to interpret the budget suggestion as the minimum amount of money that should be taken away from the treatment group.  You can see these values in the <code>Investment</code> column from the output of <code>GeoLiftMarketSelection</code>.</p><p>If your treatment group is currently investing less than the required budget, then it will be hard to detect an effect, given that the CPIC is accurate.  You should try to select treatment setups that have a current investment that is below the absolute value of the required budget.  If there are no feasible options,  we suggest increasing the budget for all markets within the control group to ensure that the minimum amount of investment in the treatment group is met.  While this could change Business As Usual media circumstances, it becomes necessary in order to run a well-powered experiment. A good ad hoc rule for these cases is to compute the extra budget needed by calculating the difference between the required budget and the current investment in treatment and scaling that by the treatment investment share over total investment.  This will give you the value that you need to put up to run a successful experiment.</p><p><img src="https://github.com/facebookincubator/GeoLift/blob/main/website/static/img/ExtraInvestment.png?raw=true" alt="ExtraInvestment"/></p><h3>Keep an eye on the weights for the counterfactual.</h3><p>When setting up the test, you can access the weights for each of the control locations with the <code>GetWeights()</code> method.  This will show you how each of the locations that will not be treated (shown media ads) will be weighted within the counterfactual.</p><p>When running an Inverse GeoLift, it’s important to guarantee that you will show media ads in these locations.  If available, you can validate this by getting an investment report by location and ensuring that all locations with a positive weight in the counterfactual from GeoLift are being shown ads.  If this condition is not met, we could be observing a very small treatment effect due to dilution of media within the control group, when the real treatment effect could be large.</p><h3>Look for symmetric power curves</h3><p>A symmetric power curve with respect to the y axis will guarantee that there are no considerable differences for a particular setup when changing from a Standard to an Inverse GeoLift.  This is another guarantee that our assumptions for these types of tests hold.  You can visualize this by running the <code>GeoLiftPower()</code> function with positive and negative effects, a larger <code>lookback_window</code> and plotting its output.  You can check for examples of what it should look like in our Github Walkthrough.</p><h3>Calculate the Treatment’s CPIC</h3><p>At the end of your experiment, you will want to know how much each incremental action in the treatment group cost.  Since you did not invest in the treatment, you need to estimate the budget in that group.  In order to do so, you can calculate the sum of GeoLift weights from the counterfactual and multiply them by the investment per location in the control.  Dividing it by the incremental conversions will give you the Cost Per Incremental Conversion.</p><p><img src="https://github.com/facebookincubator/GeoLift/blob/main/website/static/img/CPICEquation.png?raw=true" alt="CPIC"/></p><p>Where t0 represents the last pre-treatment time-stamp, T represents the treatment end, and N represents the number of units in the pool of controls.</p><h2>What’s up next?</h2><p>Stay tuned for our next blog posts, related to topics like:</p><ul><li>Calibrating your MMM model with GeoLift.</li><li>What should my lookback window be?</li><li>When should our GeoLift test start?</li></ul><h2>Want to try out your first Inverse GeoLift?</h2><p>Install our Github package by <a href="https://github.com/facebookincubator/GeoLift#installing-geolift">following this link</a>, or join our Facebook Group if you have further questions on our open source tool!</p>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Launching GeoLift v2.3 - Streamlined and Improved Power Calculations]]></title>
            <link>https://facebookincubator.github.io/GeoLift/blog/geolift-v23</link>
            <guid>geolift-v23</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 03 Mar 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[GeoLift v2.3 Release]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>GeoLift v2.3 Release</h2><h3>TL;DR</h3><ul><li>The new version of the GeoLift code makes the pre-test analysis (Power Analysis and Market Selection) easier than ever before! The entire process is now handled by a single function: <code>GeoLiftMarketSelection()</code>.</li><li>The new package contains dozens of new features, functionalities, and bug fixes.</li><li>A new and improved walkthrough guide is available to help internal and external users run their GeoLift tests from start to finish!</li></ul><h2>GeoLift v2.3: Power Calculations Made Easier</h2><p>Following the feedback we received, we re-built the Power Calculation and Market Selection functionalities from the ground up! The new code makes this process easier, more streamlined, and more powerful than ever before.</p><h3>What&#x27;s New?</h3><ul><li>We&#x27;ve <strong>streamlined the entire Power Analysis and Market Selection process into a single function</strong>: <code>GeoLiftMarketSelection()</code>.</li><li>Previously, the process to select the test markets was very convoluted and involved going through several functions: <code>NumberLocations()</code>, <code>GeoLiftPower.search()</code>, <code>GeoLiftPowerFinder()</code>, and <code>GeoLiftPower()</code>. The new function, <code>GeoLiftMarketSelection()</code>, aggregates all of their functionalities and even improves upon them.</li><li>We&#x27;re soft-deprecating the <code>NumberLocations()</code>, <code>GeoLiftPower.search()</code>, <code>GeoLiftPowerFinder()</code>, and <code>GeoLiftPower()</code>. The development of these functions is now considered complete and they&#x27;re now superseeded by <code>GeoLiftMarketSelection()</code>.</li><li>We&#x27;ve included <strong>two</strong> new important <strong>metrics</strong> that can help us make better decisions when comparing between different test market candidates: <em>Average_MDE</em> and <em>abs_lift_in_zero</em>.</li><li>A <strong>new and improved ranking system</strong> takes into consideration all key model performance metrics to identify the best test markets for a given set-up.</li><li>We&#x27;ve added the option for <strong>one tailed tests</strong>.  These make the GeoLift model much more powerful than it was before, by simply changing the test hypothesis we want to validate.  Now you can chose from <em>Positive</em>, <em>Negative</em> and <em>Total</em> tests in the inference section and one sided or two sided tests in the power section.</li><li>The Market Selection process is more flexible and customizable than before! You can now include <strong>additional test constraints</strong> to focus only on the tests that make sense for our client. These are: the available budget (<em>budget</em>), acceptable holdout ranges (<em>holdout</em>), test markets we want to force into the test regions (<em>include_markets</em>), and markets that shouldn&#x27;t be considered as eligible test regions (<em>exclude_markets</em>).</li><li>We&#x27;ve added a <strong>new plotting method for GeoLiftMarketSelection</strong> objects. Through this method you can easily plot different test market selections and compare their model fit, MDE, and power curves! Plus, they lines have the GeoLift colors!
<img src="/img/GeoLiftMarketSelection_Plot2-1.png" alt="PlotATTBest"/></li><li>The <strong>new function</strong>: <code>GetWeights()</code> makes it easy to save the synthetic control weights into a data frame for further analysis.</li><li>To aid with <strong>MMM calibrations</strong>, we&#x27;ve included a new parameter in the Market Selection/Power Analysis function: <em>Correlations</em>. Setting it to TRUE allows the user to analyze the similarities between test and the control regions.</li><li>You can also <strong>plot historical similarities between test and control regions</strong> with <code>plotCorrels()</code>.
<img src="/img/plotcorrels.png" alt="PlotATTBest"/></li><li>A revamped <strong>GeoLift walkthrough vignette has been launched</strong> to accompany the new version of the package. This new material provides much more detailed explanation on our model, it&#x27;s parameters, how to run a study, and how to interpret the results.</li><li>We&#x27;ve <strong>fixed multiple bug and errors</strong> across the package (thanks for the feedback!).</li><li>Thanks to all of these changes, we&#x27;ve <strong>significantly reduced the total time needed in pre-test calculations!</strong></li></ul>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A Brief Review of Geo Measurement Approaches]]></title>
            <link>https://facebookincubator.github.io/GeoLift/blog/geo-measurement-review</link>
            <guid>geo-measurement-review</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 02 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Intro to Quasi-Experiments]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>Intro to Quasi-Experiments</h2><p>While Randomized Control Trials remain as the gold-standard for causal analysis, good RCTs are hard to come by given how complicated and expensive they are to execute. In particular, their reliance on randomization, which is the foundation for their unbiasedness, is often one of the factors that limit their usage. Some of the most common drawbacks of randomly splitting a population into test and control groups are:</p><ul><li>Implementing and maintaining the randomization throughout the experiment requires a robust infrastructure.</li><li>Limiting the treatment to only the test group can be unethical. For example, restraining the control group from receiving life-saving medicine is wrong. This could also be the case for PSAs.</li><li>It is common to have constraints on which units can be part of the test and control groups. These constraints prevent us from having a good randomization. For example, in a geo-experiment there are often a set of locations that need to receive the treatment and some units can’t get the treatment, which severely reduces the possible randomizations and greatly reduces the experiment’s precision.</li></ul><p>Quasi-experimental methods offer a great alternative to measure the impact of a treatment (such as an ad campaign) whenever randomization is not logistically feasible or ethical. These methods differ from traditional RCTs in that they don’t use randomization to select the test and control groups. This gives us a lot of additional flexibility in the experimental design at the cost of a typically larger sample sizes and additional modeling assumptions. Nevertheless, under the right circumstances quasi-experiments provide a great alternative to measure a treatment and can empower advertisers that have been historically unable to use incrementality to start taking decisions based on Lift. Moreover, one of the most commonly used type of quasi-experiments are geo tests, in which the units of experimentation are geographical areas such as zip-codes, cities, regions, or states. In this note we will do a historical review of the most commonly used approaches to geographic quasi-experimentation and compare them to GeoLift.</p>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Welcome]]></title>
            <link>https://facebookincubator.github.io/GeoLift/blog/welcome</link>
            <guid>welcome</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Welcome to GeoLift's blog where we discuss anything related to:]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong>Welcome to GeoLift&#x27;s blog</strong> where we discuss anything related to:</p><ul><li>Geo-testing</li><li>Incrementality and Lift</li><li>GeoLift</li><li>and more!</li></ul>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>